<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Graalvm on @jeqo</title><link>https://jeqo.github.io/tags/graalvm/</link><description>Recent content in Graalvm on @jeqo</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jeqo.github.io/tags/graalvm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Kafka client applications with GraalVM</title><link>https://jeqo.github.io/posts/2022-03-18-kafka-clients-graalvm/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jeqo.github.io/posts/2022-03-18-kafka-clients-graalvm/</guid><description>&lt;p>Shipping CLI binaries with Java hasn&amp;rsquo;t been the most user-friendly experience.
Java is required to be installed on the client-side, starting Java applications (e.g. executable JAR) tend to be slower than to binary applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>GraalVM, and specifically &lt;a href="https://www.graalvm.org/22.0/reference-manual/native-image/">native-image&lt;/a> tooling, is aimed to tackle most of these issues with Java by enable building native binaries from Java applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Even though this has been supported for a while now, reflection and other practices require additional configurations that make this process either unsupported or very cumbersome to implement.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With the arrival of new frameworks that target the benefits of GraalVM, like &lt;a href="https://micronaut.io/">Micronaut&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://quarkus.io/">Quarkus&lt;/a>, it started to be possible and simpler to implement applications that included Kafka clients, and package them as native binaries.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This post is going to explore the steps to package &lt;em>vanilla&lt;/em> Kafka client applications —i.e. no framework— as native binaries.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Releasing OS-specific GraalVM native image binaries easier with JReleaser</title><link>https://jeqo.github.io/notes/2022-03-01-jreleaser-graalvm-native-image/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://jeqo.github.io/notes/2022-03-01-jreleaser-graalvm-native-image/</guid><description>&lt;p>Packaging and releasing Java applications (e.g. CLI) tend to be cumbersome, and the user-experience tended not to be the best as users have to download a valid version of JRE, etc.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>