<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tils on @jeqo</title>
    <link>https://jeqo.github.io/til/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tils on @jeqo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Copyright @jeqo</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jeqo.github.io/til/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>reload4j as drop-in replacement for log4j 1.x</title>
      <link>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2022-01-25-reload4j/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2022-01-25-reload4j/</guid>
      <description>TIL there is a drop-in replacement for log4j 1.x: Reload4j.
It continues fixing security issues, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t require changing application logic. Dropping JAR to the classpath, removing previous log4j-1.* JARs should be enough to get the latest patches.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ansible has a debug mode to pause and troubleshoot</title>
      <link>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2022-01-21-ansible-debug/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2022-01-21-ansible-debug/</guid>
      <description>I have been running Ansible for a while now. My usual/naive way of debugging has always been adding a debug module[1], and get the execution running til that point.
I figured that there are better ways to deal with this[2]. By using the debug mode, tasks will stop when failing (by default) and you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to introspect into the task, variables, and context when things failed. Even better, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to re-execute if there was a transient error.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changing Kafka Broker&#39;s rack</title>
      <link>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-10-kafka-change-rack/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-10-kafka-change-rack/</guid>
      <description>Kafka broker configuration includes a rack label to define the location of the broker. This is useful when placing replicas across the cluster to ensure replicas are spread across locations as evenly as possible.
This label may need to change for different reasons. One I found today is if you want to redefine locations to support Multi-Region clusters and Observers.
If there are existing topics, and previous rack labels were already used when creating the topics, then the placement may not match the new topology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kafka Producer idempotency is enabled by default since 3.0</title>
      <link>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-09-kafka-v3-idempotent-acks-all/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-09-kafka-v3-idempotent-acks-all/</guid>
      <description>Since Apache Kafka 3.0, Producers come with enable.idempotency=true which leads to acks=all, along with other changes enforced by idempotency.
This means by default Producers will be balanced between latency (no batching) and durability — different from previous versions where the main goal was to reduce latency even by risking durability with acks=1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reducing `acks` doesn&#39;t help to reduce end-to-end latency</title>
      <link>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-09-kafka-reducing-acks-and-latency/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-09-kafka-reducing-acks-and-latency/</guid>
      <description>Kafka Producers enforce durability across replicas by setting acks=all (default since v3.0). As enforcing this guarantee requires waiting for replicas to sync, this increases latency; and reducing it tends to give the impression that latency gets reduced overall.
When looking at the end-to-end latency (including production and consumption) this ends up not being the case:
Records are only available for consumption once the replicas have been updated and the leader can increase the high watermark.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use min.insync.replicas for fault-tolerance</title>
      <link>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-02-kafka-min-isr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-02-kafka-min-isr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Things to remember:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topic replication factor is not enough to guarantee fault-tolerance. If &lt;code&gt;min.insync.replicas&lt;/code&gt; is not defined i.e. 1, then data could potentially be lost.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;acks=all&lt;/code&gt; will force replica leader to wait for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; brokers in the ISR, not only the &lt;code&gt;min.insync.replicas&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If replicas available are equal to minimum ISR, then the topic partitions are at the edge of losing availability. If one broker becomes unavailable (e.g. restarting), then producers will fail to write data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topic configuration is inherited from the server. If broker configuration changes, it affects the &lt;em&gt;existing&lt;/em&gt; topics. Keep the topic defaults, unless it needs to be different than broker default for easier maintenance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About TILs</title>
      <link>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-01-about-til/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-01-about-til/</guid>
      <description>Today I learned about Today-I-Learned posts from Simon Willison: https://til.simonwillison.net/ and found it super cool, so I decided to try out, let&amp;rsquo;s see how it goes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
