<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ops on @jeqo</title>
    <link>https://jeqo.github.io/categories/ops/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ops on @jeqo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Copyright @jeqo</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jeqo.github.io/categories/ops/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Kafka data loss scenarios</title>
      <link>https://jeqo.github.io/posts/2021-12-10-kafka-data-loss/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeqo.github.io/posts/2021-12-10-kafka-data-loss/</guid>
      <description>Kafka topic partitions are replicated across brokers. Data loss happens when the brokers where replicas are located are unavailable or have fully failed. The worst scenario — and where is no much to do — is when all the brokers fail; then no remediation is possible. Replication allows to increase redundancy so this scenarios is less likely to happen.
The following scenarios show different trade-offs that could increase the risk of lossing data:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reducing `acks` doesn&#39;t help to reduce end-to-end latency</title>
      <link>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-09-kafka-reducing-acks-and-latency/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-09-kafka-reducing-acks-and-latency/</guid>
      <description>Kafka Producers enforce durability across replicas by setting acks=all (default since v3.0). As enforcing this guarantee requires waiting for replicas to sync, this increases latency; and reducing it tends to give the impression that latency gets reduced overall.
When looking at the end-to-end latency (including production and consumption) this ends up not being the case:
Records are only available for consumption once the replicas have been updated and the leader can increase the high watermark.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use min.insync.replicas for fault-tolerance</title>
      <link>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-02-kafka-min-isr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jeqo.github.io/til/2021-12-02-kafka-min-isr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Things to remember:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topic replication factor is not enough to guarantee fault-tolerance. If &lt;code&gt;min.insync.replicas&lt;/code&gt; is not defined i.e. 1, then data could potentially be lost.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;acks=all&lt;/code&gt; will force replica leader to wait for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; brokers in the ISR, not only the &lt;code&gt;min.insync.replicas&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If replicas available are equal to minimum ISR, then the topic partitions are at the edge of losing availability. If one broker becomes unavailable (e.g. restarting), then producers will fail to write data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topic configuration is inherited from the server. If broker configuration changes, it affects the &lt;em&gt;existing&lt;/em&gt; topics. Keep the topic defaults, unless it needs to be different than broker default for easier maintenance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
